PERSONAL STATEMENT

I am a second year MSc student in the Department of Biomedical and Molecular Sciences at Queen's University.

My research interest is in studying complex human diseases using bioinformatics and data mining approaches, in order to uncover disease mechanisms and assist in drug target discovery.

My current work investigates the chemotherapy response in ovarian cancer patients through RNA-seq data analysis. My aim is to identify gene expression networks, miRNA networks, and genomic variants that are associated with a poor chemotherapy response. I expect that these results will highlight the underlying chemotherapy resistance pathways, and provide new targets for patient screening and pharmaceutical applications.

My practical skills include:

Programming languages: R, Python, Matlab, Linux (bash), Java, C, Haskell, Prolog

Bioinformatics: Next-generation sequencing and microarray data preprocessing and analysis

tools, bioinformatics databases; molecular dynamics software

Machine learning skills: classification, clustering, prediction, pattern recognition algorithms

EDUCATION

Master of Science 2017 – Present

Experimental Medicine, Department of Biomedical and Molecular Sciences

Queen's University, Kingston, ON

Supervisor: Dr. Qingling Duan

Thesis: Biological networks and genomic variants modulating chemotherapy response in ovarian

cancer

Bachelor of Science (Honours)

2013 - 2017

Biology major, Computer Science minor

Queen's University, Kingston, ON

Supervisor: Dr. Paul G. Young

Thesis: Copper induced stress response and programmed cell death in Saccharomyces cerevisiae

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

MSc Candidate May 2017 – Present

Computational Genomics Laboratory

Department of Biomedical and Molecular Sciences, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

- Supervisor: Dr. Qingling Duan
- Identified gene networks and variants involved in chemotherapy response
- Designed RNA-Seq and Whole Exome Sequencing data processing pipeline
- Performed transcriptome, miRNA, eQTL and genomic variant analysis on data from The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA)

Undergraduate Research Thesis

Sept. 2016 - Apr. 2017

Department of Biology, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

- Supervisor: Dr. Paul G. Young
- Undergraduate 12-unit thesis studying programmed cell death in S. cerevisiae
- Trained in RNA-Seq data processing and transcriptome analysis
- Thesis submitted to BIOL 537 research course (select students only)

QGEM Dry Lab Executive

May 2016 - Oct. 2016

Queen's International Genetically Engineered Machine (iGEM) Team

Department of Biomedical and Molecular Sciences, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

- Head of the Dry Lab research team in the Queen's iGEM team for 2016
- Summer research project studying non-ribosomal peptide synthesis
- Trained in molecular dynamics and modeling of protein interactions, machine learning algorithms and energy optimization
- Part of QGEM's 2016 research project for participation at the International Genetically Engineered Machine competition

Research Assistant Oct. 2015 – Jul. 2016

Department of Biology, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

- Supervisor: Dr. Tomas Babak
- Collaborated with Dr. Brian DeVeale (University of California, San Francisco)
- Performed statistical analysis and visualization of data for a genome-wide association study on schizophrenia

Lab Assistant Internship

Jun. 2015 - Jul. 2015

IVF facility, Interbalkan Medical Center, Thessaloniki, Greece

- Supervisor: Dr. Ioannis Tziafetas
- Assisted in laboratory organisation and maintenance in a professional setting, shadowed in handling of human embryonic cells

Lab Volunteer Jan. 2015 – Oct. 2015

Department of Biology, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

- Supervisor: Dr. Stephen C. Lougheed
- Performed tissue sampling and preservation of native Ontario snakes to investigate species distribution
- Assisted with genetic analysis (PCR, gel electrophoresis) of collected samples and participated in field work

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant Sept. 2018 – Dec. 2018

Department of Biomedical and Molecular Sciences, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

- Instructor: Dr. Qingling Duan
- BMED 370: Genetics and Genomics
- Participated in assignment and rubric design, assisted students in online course, marked student assignments

Teaching Assistant

Jan. 2018 – Apr. 2018

Department of Biomedical and Molecular Sciences, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

- Instructor: Dr. Qingling Duan
- BMED 370: Genetics and Genomics
- Assisted students in online course, marked student assignments

Lab Teaching Assistant

Sept. 2017 - Dec. 2017

Department of Biology, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

- Instructor: Dr. Robert Snetsinger
- BIOL 102: Introductory Biology of Cells
- Oversaw and marked laboratory sections of the course

Teaching Assistant

Sept. 2016 - Dec. 2016

School of Computing, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

- Instructor: Dr. Wendy Powley
- CISC 101: Elements of Computer Science, the Python version of the introductory programming course
- Marked assignments and exams, held lab office hours for course help, presented a guest lecture on programming exercises

Teaching Assistant

Sept. 2015 - Dec. 2015

School of Computing, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

- Instructor: Dr. David Skillicorn
- CISC 101: Elements of Computer Science, the Matlab version of the introductory programming course, with an emphasis on data mining techniques
- Oversaw and marked the laboratory component of the course, managed a class of 40 students and improved their understanding of data analysis and statistics methods

AWARDS

Conference Travel Award (CTA)

22 Oct. 2018

Queen's University, Kingston, ON

- Awarded to select graduate students in the Department of Biomedical and Molecular Sciences
- Funded travel to the American Society of Human Genetics 2018 Meeting
- Funds awarded: \$ 250 (CAD)

International Tuition Award (ITA)

2017 - 2018

Queen's University, Kingston, ON

- Scholarship awarded to select international graduate students
- Funds awarded: \$5,000 (CAD)

Principal's Scholarship

2013 - 2014

Queen's University, Kingston, ON

- Scholarship awarded to students whose high school average is greater than 95%
- Funds awarded: \$ 6,000 (CAD)

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

Professional Extension

CISC 859: Pattern Recognition (Audit)

Jan. - Apr. 2019

Goodwin Hall, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

ASHG/IGES/ISCB Joint Symposium:

16 Oct. 2018

Working with Big Data in the Cloud--Research and Privacy

San Diego Convention Center, San Diego, CA

HPC Summer School 2018: Bioinformatics Workflows

3 Aug. 2018

Chernoff Hall, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

The High Performance Computing Symposium (HPCS)

6-9 Jun. 2017

Queen's University, Kingston, Ontario

Professional Memberships

The American Society of Human Genetics

2018 – Present

PUBLICATIONS

In preparation

- 1. **Topouza**, **D.G.**, Choi, J., Nesdoly, S., and Duan, Q.L. *Biological networks and genomic variants modulating platinum chemotherapy response in high-grade serous cystadenocarcinoma*
- 2. **Topouza**, **D.G.**, Choi, J., Nesdoly, S., and Duan, Q.L. *miRNA isoforms and networks associated with platinum chemotherapy response in high-grade serous cystadenocarcinoma*
- 3. Choi, J., Tarnouskaya, A., Nesdoly, S., **Topouza**, **D.G.**, Bajwa, K., Koti, M., and Duan, Q.L. *Coexpression gene networks associated with therapeutic response in high-grade serous epithelian ovarian cancer*

PUBLISHED ABSTRACTS

- 1. **Topouza**, **D.G.**, Choi, J., Nesdoly, S., and Duan, Q.L. *Biological networks modulating chemotherapy response in ovarian cancer; (Abstract #685)*. The 68th Annual Meeting of The American Society of Human Genetics (2018).
- 2. **Topouza**, **D.G.**, Choi, J., Nesdoly, S., and Duan, Q.L. *Gene expression networks modulating chemotherapy response in ovarian cancer*. The 3rd Annual Toronto RNA Enthusiast's Day (2018).
- 3. **Topouza**, **D.G.**, Choi, J., Nesdoly, S., and Duan, Q.L. *Biological networks modulating chemotherapy response in ovarian cancer*. The 21st Annual Scientific Meeting for Health Science Research Trainees (2018).
- 4. Chiriac, D.S., **Topouza**, **D.G.**, Tanwani, J., Wang, Y., and Allingham, J. *Pharming The Blues: Improving biosynthesis of natural products.* The 12th Annual International Genetically Engineered Machine (iGEM) Competition (2016).

POSTERS AND PRESENTATIONS

Oral presentations

1. Masters Student Symposium Seminar Presentation

24 Apr. 2018

Botterell Hall, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

A pharmacogenomics analysis of biological networks regulating chemotherapy response among ovarian cancer patients

2. Undergraduate Thesis Seminar Presentation

11 Nov. 2016

Biosciences Complex, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

Programmed cell death in the unicellular eukaryote Saccharomyces cerevisiae

Poster presentations

3. American Society of Human Genetics (ASHG) 2018 Meeting

16-20 Oct. 2018

San Diego Convention Center, San Diego, CA

Topouza, **D.G.**, Choi, J., Nesdoly, S., and Duan, Q.L. *Biological networks modulating chemotherapy response in ovarian cancer;* (Abstract #685)

4. Toronto RNA Enthusiast's Day

31 Jul. 2018

SickKids Peter Gilgan Centre for Research and Learning, Toronto, ON

Topouza, **D.G.**, Choi, J., Nesdoly, S., and Duan, Q.L. *Gene expression networks modulating chemotherapy response in ovarian cancer*

5. The Twenty-First Annual Scientific Meeting for Health Science Research Trainees
Biosciences Complex, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

Topouza, **D.G.**, Choi, J., Nesdoly, S., and Duan, Q.L. *Biological networks modulating chemotherapy response in ovarian cancer*

6. Undergraduate Thesis Poster Presentation

10 Mar. 2017

Biosciences Complex, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

Topouza, **D.G.**, and Young, P.G. *Programmed cell death in the unicellular eukaryote Saccharomyces cerevisiae*

7. International Genetically Engineered Machine Competition (Bronze medal)

Hynes Convention Center, Boston, MA

Chiriac, D.S., Topouza, D.G., Tanwani, J., Wang, Y., and Allingham, J. Pharming The Blues: Improving biosynthesis of natural products

8. Scinapse Undergraduate Science Case Competition (Finalist)
Western University, London, ON
Nowak, S., Thomsen, C., and Topouza, D.G. The role of mycorrhizal community assemblages in agricultural productivity